Lange, W. mss., 1780s-1950s LMC 2512
Lilly Library
Lange, W. mss.
1780s-1950s
2005
Lilly Library
Lange, Walter
LMC 2512
2 Boxes 2 standard
The Lange, W. mss., 1780s-1950s, consists of the collected autographs, correspondence, writings, and publications of scholar and collector Walter Lange.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
As a scholar of library science, Walter Lange conducted several bibliographical studies, while actively working as a rare text collector. For his Master of Arts degree, Lange wrote a dissertation on the French Revolution and the "lost Dauphin," the son of Louis XVI and Marie Antoinette, who was rumored to survive the French Revolution. Lange was also interested in the Wise Forgeries, concerning Thomas James Wise, a widely known book collector later turned out to be a forger. To investigate Wise's case, Lange exchanged correspondence with various scholars and collectors. One noteworthy part of the Lange collection is his own collection of the autographs related to the French Revolution. For several years, Lange conducted research on the rumor and the false claimants of the lost Dauphin, during which he created a collection of letters, hand-written documents, and notes of highly important figures, such as Karl Wilhelm Naudorff and Eleazar Williams, both widely known false claimants in the nineteenth century. His collection also encompasses first-hand records of the contemporaneity by French nobility and royal members, along with autographs and original letters of others who are less directly connected to the French royal family and the revolution. Besides the French Revolution, Lange's study on the Wise forgeries is also taking up a huge portion of the collection, although this part mainly consists of Lange's correspondence and book catalogues rather than firsthand texts. Lange also left a vast amount of book and autograph catalogues along with letters with other book collectors, which reflect his deep bibliographic interest in various types of rare texts.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series: I. French Revolution, II. Autographs, III. Wise Forgeries, IV. Book Catalogues and Collections, V. Political and Historical.
Scope and Content Note
French Revolution includes results of Lange's research on the French Revolution and the "Lost Dauphin," ranging from correspondence to articles and various types of historical records. Autographs consists of letters, notes, and other hand-written documents Lange collected. Wise Forgeries gathers diverse materials Lange left in his study on Thomas James Wise, famous book collector and forger. Book Catalogues and Collections encompasses numerous catalogues Lange used to collect rare texts. Political and Historical shows Lange's other minor historical studies along with records of Lange's political involvement in the Democratic Party.
Related Material
See Gerstein mss., also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 2005
Lange, Walter
- I. FRENCH REVOLUTION
  - "Louis XVII of France," thesis by W. Lange, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--from As (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--from Bs (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--from Cs (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--from Ds (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--from Es (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--from Fs (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--from Gs (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--from Hs (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--from Js (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--from Ks (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--from Ms (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--from Ns (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--from Ps (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--from Ss (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--from Vs (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--from Ws (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--with libraries and publishers (Box 1)
  - Materials by E. Merray, 1950-1965 (Box 1)
  - Articles, 1931-1941 (Box 1)
  - Book cataloges (Box 1)
  - "Lost Dauphin" bibliography (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1938-1965 (Box 1)
  - Fleur-de-lis art piece (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes loose, unbound material
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Illustration of the arrest of Louis XVI, 1799 (Box 1)
  - Letter of the family of Louis XVII (Box 1)
  - Louis XVII--Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- II. AUTOGRAPHS
  - de Moromenil, Armand Thomas Hue, 1778-1823 (Box 1)
  - Illegible, 1847 (Box 1)
  - Finance Minister [?], 1888 (Box 1)
  - Fraulein Marga Pohlis Achen [?], 1931 (Box 1)
    Folder "Bickerstaffe-Drew, Francis Browning" contains an item with the same signature as this item
  - Adalbert de Bourbon, 1814 (Box 1)
  - Bickerstaffe-Drew, Francis Browning, n. d. (Box 1)
    With 2 additional items written by other people, names illegible; the item in the folder "Fraulein Marga Pohlis Achen [?], 1931" has the same signature as one of these two additional items (the large envelope)
  - Clery, Jean Baptiste, 1792 (Box 1)
  - Day, Clarence Shepard (Box 1)
  - Edgeworth de Firmont, 1798 (Box 1)
  - Fauche-Borel, Louis, 1829 (Box 1)
  - Henry, count of Paris, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Hue, Valet-de-Chambre of Dauphin, 1817 (Box 1)
  - Knapp, F. G., 1934 (Box 1)
  - Louis, 1816 (Box 1)
  - Louis XVII, duke of Gesvres, 1785 (Box 1)
  - Louis de Bourbon, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Louis Philippe, count of Paris, 1877 (Box 1)
    1 additional item by seemingly a different person, unidentified
  - Malesherbes, defender of Louis XVI (Box 1)
  - Marie Antoinette, 1793 (Box 1)
  - Maricourt, count Rene de, 1888 (Box 1)
  - Naundorff, a Dauphin claimant, 1830 (Box 1)
  - Pelletan, Philippe-Jean, 1810 (Box 1)
  - Sabatini, Rafael, 1918-1927 (Box 1)
  - Willliams, Eleazer, a Dauphin claimant, 1820 (Box 1)
  - Willliams, Eleazer, a Dauphin claimant, 1851 (Box 1)
  - Willliams, Eleazer, a Dauphin claimant, 1854 (Box 1)
  - Willliams, Eleazer, a Dauphin claimant, n. d. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence on autographs (Box 1)
- III. WISE FORGERIES
  - Article by W. Lange (Box 1)
  - Notes by W. Lange (Box 1)
  - Articles and Reviews, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    2 copies of The Atlantic in the folder 2
  - Catalogues and booklets (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
- IV. BOOK CATALOGUES and COLLECTIONS
  - Goodspeed's bookshop catalogues, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    Folder 1: Catalogue no. 423, 457, 475; Folder 2: Catalogue no. 490, 500, 508
  - H. C. Bowen catalogue, 1882 (Box 1)
  - Howard S. Mott catalogue, no. 189 (Box 1)
  - Indiana Quarterly for Bookmen, January 1947 (Box 1)
  - J. F. Dobie catalogue, no 5 (Box 1)
  - Scribners catalogue, no. 139 (Box 1)
  - Concerning A. E. Newton (Box 1)
  - Concerning H. A. Shute, 1957-1967 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence on books, etc. (Box 2)
- V. POLITICAL and HISTORICAL
  - Booth-Lincoln materials, 1939 (Box 2)
  - Democrat materials, 1963-1968 (Box 2)
  - J. F. Kennedy materials, 1961-1964 (Box 2)
  - Appointment certificate, January 6, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Russian history (Anastasia study) (Box 2)